[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software developers got some extra time
on your hands use it to learn a new
database inner systems Iris allows you
to choose your language tools and
environment so you can collaborate build
faster and deploy more efficiently now's
your chance to try out inner systems
Iris the fastest way to build
applications Ready Set code visit inner
systems.com Iris to learn
more this is Jeremy Jung for software
engineering radio today I'm talking to
jul lurman she's a frequent conference
speaker an independent consultant and a
plural site course author today we're
going to talk about her experience
working on ORS and Entity framework
Julie welcome to software engineering
radio hey Jeremy thanks so much for
having me for those who aren't familiar
with orms what what are they and why do
we need them the first thing is the
definition so omm stands for object
relational mapper so it's a
software idea and implementation in in
many aspects for taking the concepts
that we describe as classes and
transforming them into the structure of
a relational database so you can get the
data in and out easily so the OM takes
care of that
mapping and the transformation so you
don't have to worry about writing SQL
you don't have to worry about getting
results you know structured results from
a database that are in rows and columns
and then transforming them back into
object instances so the or's do that for
you some of the most popular languages
used are object-oriented why do we
continue to store our data in a
relational database when it's so
different from our application code
there's certainly a lot of reasons for
relational databases compared to like
document databases object databases
relational databases for their structure
and normalization and tuning and it's
different kinds of storage needs I think
than when you're storing documents it's
uh sometimes it's I think more about
getting the data back out finding data
so it's one thing to be able to store it
in a way that makes sense but then when
you need to pull data together and
create relationships that aren't
naturally in those documents you know
unless you have prepared and designed
something like a document database for
every possible scenario there's also the
whole concept of event sourcing where
you know if you're just storing the
events then you can actually re persist
that data in different structures so
that it's easier for the various ways
you might Act access it also you know
relational database has been around for
a long time and it's interesting that
even with the popularity and you know
extreme power of these other kinds of
non-relational databases the nosql
databases relational databases are still
I can't say the source off the top of my
head but I've I've used them in in
conference slides they update their data
monthly but I can see these these graphs
where shows that there still about 70%
of systems out there are using
relational databases and in a lot of
cases so much Legacy data too right that
that's all going to be in relational
databases relational databases they give
us the ability to request just the data
we need that that matches a certain
condition or we can combine different
parts of our data and get just a
specific thing that we need that if we
were just dealing with a bunch of arrays
of objects or documents it might be
harder to query for a specific thing
does does that sort of match yeah
especially that unplanned data access
and another interesting thing and it's
one of those things that I think you
have to like stop and think about it to
realize the truth in it which is that
most systems most of the work you're
doing in the database is reading the
database much more than creating and
storing data that's the bigger problem
getting the data back out and and having
the
flexibility to do weird things whereas
something like a document database you
know depending on how you split it up
and keys and everything it's just more
designed uh relational databases
just it's a little easier to get at that
weird stuff you mentioned ad hoc queries
so with a relational database you can
store all your information and then you
can decide later what sort of queries or
what sort of information you want to get
out whereas you had hinted at with a a
document database you have to think
upfront about what queries you want to
to make could you elaborate a little bit
on on that I don't want to be
generalizing too much because there's
all kinds of other factors that might
come in especially when talking about
huge amounts of data for like machine
learning and things like that there's a
point you know the there's pros and cons
to both of them and like I mentioned
with event sourcing ways to kind of have
your cake and eat it too when I look for
example at documentation for meure
Cosmos DB that's what the document
database that I have the most
familiarity with one of the most
important documents is that upfront
design and that design bleeds into how
you're modeling your data in your
application so that you can store it
fluidly into the document database so
it's really really important now I don't
want to conflate this with you know the
kind of the beauty of some system like
document database how that aligns so
much more nicely for
persistence and most of you you know
getting data in and getting data out
when we're talking about uh domain drum
design where you don't want to worry
about your persistence like just focus
on the domain and then you know we can
always figure out how to get the data in
and out right we got patterns for that
but it is interesting if something like
a document database more naturally
aligns with your objects right so that
flows nicely in however it's still
really important to be considerate of
how you're breaking up that data in in
the way you store it what you know what
your graphs are going to be how you
going to you know maybe it's easy to get
it in this way but then what about when
you're getting it out what about
different different perspectives that
you have so I want to be really careful
about
comparing and
contrasting the document DB versus
relational
DB I want to stop at some level of that
because there's always going to be
debate and argument about that however
you know one of the nice things about an
an omm is it does take away some of that
pain that we normally would have when
we're writing applications and writing
that data access layer where we have to
say Okay I want this now I have to
figure out the SQL statement you know or
call a stored procedure or however I'm
going to do it you know whether I'm
getting data in or getting data out and
then getting you know and then I have to
transform my objects into the SQL right
or get data back and then I have to read
through that data and instantiate
objects and stuff all the values into
those objects that's the stuff that the
OM can repetitive like bull work right
uh writing writing all that stuff so
that's what the orms do I think what of
the the next big question that comes up
then is yeah but my squel is always
going to be better than some generic
thing that ANM is going to build for me
right the general advice for that is for
many cases what the OM does will the
performance will be
just perfectly fine right and then
there's going to be the cases where the
performance isn't good so then you can
you know use your own store procedures
use your views but a lot of the omm
certainly the one I focus on which is
Microsoft's Entity
framework has the ability to also
interact with stored procedures and
Views and do mappings to views and and
things like that so so people don't
realize that right that
but maybe 80% of the SQL that Entity
framework is going to write whether it's
for queries or for pushing data into the
database maybe 80% of that is perfectly
fine right and then 20% of that do
performance testing and go yeah that's
not I can do better I can do better I
can do better I can do better and fix
those up I want to step back a little
and walk through some of the features of
OMS that you had mentioned okay one of
them was not necessarily having to write
SQL so you have some alternative query
language that the omm is providing so
what are some of the benefits of that
like why would somebody not just jump
straight to SQL and would instead use
this SQL like query language well again
I'd have to kind of focus on net and
luckily I know you do a little bit of
net programming so you probably are
familiar with link the query language
that's built into net into you know C
and the net languages it's a much
simpler expression than SQL and it's
much more code like and like if you're
writing a SQL string to put in to your
application we want to use story
procedures and Views but let's say
you're just writing raw SQL right you're
writing a string and you're crossing
your fingers that you got it right right
that there's no typos but also that
you've written it correctly but if
you're using something like link which
is part of the language then you've got
all the advantages of the the language
syntax and you know intellisense and
here's my object what are my methods
that are available all popping up so all
you know you don't have to worry about
magic strings I think that's really key
and you don't have to know SQL Concepts
really so with Entity framework at the
very very beginning the team actually it
came out of Microsoft research the team
that had created that started with a
sequel like language to do it but then
link was also created at Microsoft uh by
the C team and then link was originally
created for
objects um so you can use that for
writing queries just across your objects
I wouldn't say link was evolved but a
link version that applied to Entity
framework was created so then and there
was also link to SQL um which was a much
lighter weight omm that was also created
within Microsoft so you're using the
almost the same link lot of the methods
are shared some are more specific to
Entity framework there's another benefit
like I use Link for all kinds of things
in my code not just for database the
database interaction with anty framework
I use Link just when I'm working with
arrays right working with data in
objects in memory so I've also got this
common syntax I already know how to use
it right so there's just some special
features of it that are specific to
using enti framework so there's all
kinds of benefits and the best benefit
was it enabled me to essentially forget
SQL like you know forget how to write
t-sql if I have to write raw tsql I have
to Google it right after all these years
of coding but but I don't mind with link
this was a query language that was
already built into
C and it also VB vb.net
right sharp uh so so all of the the
languages that run on the net
runtime and so the developer may already
be familiar with this query language and
they can apply it to making queries to a
database rather than having to learn SQL
which be would be an entirely new
language to the developer yes and not
just that but I don't have to learn tsql
and oql and psql right so the different
providers so there's like all kinds of
different database providers for Entity
framework and we have you know the same
for other RMS I feel a little bad just
focusing on EF but that that's my area
of expertise but the
providers are the ones that do that
transformation so Entity framework
iterates over the query a few times and
creates a query tree and then the query
tree is passed on to the provider which
then does the rest of the transformation
into its particular sequel right so I
actually go back and forth between
between SQL Server SQL light and
postgress those SQL Server is what I'm
most familiar with but I can use sqlite
and postgress and there's a lot of
generic common stuff right so as a
matter of fact the way link for Entity
framework is built that's just one thing
and then the providers figure it out so
if you need something that's really
specific to SQL Server that doesn't work
in postgress or something in post grass
that doesn't work in SQL light there
might be an extension that lets you tap
into that particular thing right or you
know or call a stored procedure except
you wouldn't do that in SQL light
because they don't have stored
procedures
interestingly kind of tapping back to
talking about document
databases there is a provider for Azure
Cosmos TV Okay so we've got an object
relational map
that maps to a nonrelational
database so the reason that exists is
because there was a lot of people that
said I really am familiar with Entity
framework I've been using it for years
we're going to be using Cosmos DB can't
I just use that so that exists and Azure
has a
SQL I don't want to say language oh you
know can use SQL has a SQL I'll just say
SQL language for accessing but you can
also there's other apis that are used
also you it's not all SQL but because it
has the SQL construct you know the
providers kind of already know how to
build SQL so it's just we'll build the
SQL that Azure works so it's not solving
the problem that we have with relational
databases which is you know that we've
got this rows and columns structure and
we need to do this translation all the
time the problem it was solving that
provider is solving by linking Entity
framework and the document database is I
already really know how to use Entity
framework and here I am just I'm just
doing some queries and persisting some
data why do I have to learn a whole new
API you're you're saying that even with
a document store you might be able to
use the same query language that's built
into your orm with a relational database
you have joins and things like that that
allow you to connect all your tables
together and and do all these different
types of queries whereas with a document
database I usually associate those with
not having joins is that also the case
with this document database that you're
referring to with with Cosmos DB I've
written only tiny little minimal SQL for
accessing it used to be called document
DB Cosmos DB directly so can't off the
top of my head remember how that sequel
works that out if you've got you know if
you've got to pull multiple documents
together I don't know but what's nice is
that in your code you don't have to
worry about that stuff oh God inner
joins and outer joins and all like oh my
God I can't I can't write that stuff
anyway so link makes sense to me I know
it really well right so I don't have
have to worry about that it it sounds
like at a a high level you get this
query language that's built into the
language is more similar to the other
code you would write and you also get
these compile time guarantees autoc
completion so that you know what things
you're allowed to call versus SQL where
like you were saying it's you have this
giant string and you you hope that hope
you got it right and don't really know
until you query
so there's a lot of benefits with an omm
you were also talking about how when you
don't have an omm you have to write your
own mapping between after you've done
your SQL query you get some data that's
in the form of just a set of records and
you have to convert those into your
objects that are native to your
application and so basically the OM is
is taking care of a lot of the you could
say say repetitive or or busy work that
you would normally have to do to be fair
there are mappers there are programs
that are mappers or apis that are
mappers like automapper for net right so
the connection string like I don't have
to worry about the connection you know
creating connections and all that kind
of stuff either with the with the omm
but you know something like automapper
you can have a data model that really
matches your your database schema and
you can have a domain model that matches
the business problem you're trying to
solve and then you can use something
like automapper to say okay like here's
what customer looks like in my
application here's what customer looks
like in this other data model that's
going to go to my datab that map matches
my database really easily and automapper
lets you say this goes with this this
goes with that blah blah blah blah blah
so that stuff does exist and and there
also other you know lighter much Entity
framework is a big thing it does a lot
there are certainly lighter weight omms
that they don't do as much of that take
away as much of that work however if you
need to squeak every little millisecond
out of your performance there's an open
source omm called Dapper and it was
built built by by the team that writes
stack Overflow because they definitely
needed to squeak every Mill second of
performance out of of their data access
there was no question about that so with
Dapper it takes care of some of the
stuff for you some of that creating the
connections and materializing objects
for you but you still write your own
sequel because they needed to tightly
control the SQL to make sure because
it's more direct it doesn't have lots of
things happening in between that Entity
framework does and there's lots of you
know dials in Entity framework where you
can impact how much work it's doing and
how many how much resources it's using
so my understanding with whether you
would use Entity framework versus one of
these smaller OMS or or more basic
mapper is it sounded like performance
and so it it sounds like maybe you would
default to using something like Entity
framework and then only dropping down to
something like Dapper if you were having
performance issues is is that where your
perspective comes from not sure if I
would wait until I'm having performance
issues I think people sometimes will
make that decision in advance but in an
interesting plan of attack you know so
that you can benefit from the Simplicity
of using Entity framework so you don't
have to write the SQL Etc is for example
using kind of a cqrs pattern right so
you know so you're separating the
commands and the queries separating
pushing data into the database and the
queries because it's usually the queries
where you need to really really focus on
the performance and worry about the
performance so some people will use cqs
and let Entity framework take care of
all the writing and let Dapper take care
of all the reading so they're designing
their application so things are not not
the business logic but you know the the
layer of the application that's taken
care of the persistence so designing it
so that those are completely separate so
oh I'm doing writing so we're spinning
up Dapper and we're going to actually
the other way around I'm doing I'm
writing so I'm going to spin up Entity
framework context and you know say go
ahead save changes or I'm doing a query
and I'm writing my own SQL because I
trust it right so now I'm going to spin
up Dapper and execute that SQL let it
create the create my objects for me so
it sounds like that might be it might be
better to actually decide that up front
is figuring out what is the amount of
load I'm going to get in my application
what are the types of queries I'm going
to be using for writing and reading data
and then from there figuring out should
I use Dapper should I use Entity
framework or you know there's some
amount of testing and exploration you
would need to do you know proof of
concept stuff I think you might want to
do first because I think Entity
framework query performance surprises
people a lot like it's a lot better than
people presume it's going to be so yeah
I would definitely do some proof of
concept before going that route because
it's it's certainly a lot easier to just
use one thing all the way through
however you know if you've got things
you know applying separation of concerns
and you know things are broken up then
it's not as traumatic to say you know
for this bit it is running a little
slowly and let's just use Dapper but
it's if it's separated
out then it's easier to just say yeah
let's just yeah let's just change over
to that being our infrastructure are
there workloads in a general sense that
you you would say that NTI framework
performs worse in than others for
example an app with a heavy right
workload you know would that be an issue
in Entity framework just are there
examples of of specific types of
applications I I don't know if it's
workload compared more
to structure you know schema or what it
is you're trying to get at you know
sometimes it's how your model is
designed right so there are just some
places that any Frameworks not going to
just not going to be able to do
something as well as your own sequel I
had an example this was years ago so
Entity framework was not in its infancy
but it was like EF for and I had a
client who well they had gone down kind
of a not great path of implementing
Entity framework in in their software
that's used across a big Enterprise They
had created one big huge model for
everybody to use so that mod one model
was responsible for you know no matter
what you were doing you had to use that
model just pulling that model into
memory was a lot of work for Entity
framework but it created a lot of
problems for the teams who were stuck
using that because of the way they had
set that up they had this common
query that would only return one piece
one row they were looking for one row
but because of the way they had designed
this model Entity framework had to go
through all kinds of uh all kinds of
Hoops to create the sequel to get at
this one piece of data to to write this
query and it was taking it was an oracle
it was taking two minutes to execute and
they're like what do we do
and I looked at it I said just write a
stored procedure do not you know like
you can't it's too late to change this
model because everything's dependent on
it so just write a stored procedure and
the stored procedure took 9 milliseconds
they're like okay we can you know we can
pay you for the whole three days you can
go home now if you want that was worth
it yeah and so it sounds like though
that's not so much a choice of not using
nity framework as it is you're still
using Entity framework but you're using
it to make a request to a store
procedure in the database similarly to
how you could probably send raw SQL from
Entity framework yes so you can still
take advantage of that so we're still
using NTI framework and saying hey I
don't want you to write the SQL just
execute this for me and so that's still
taking advantage of the fact that it
knows it SQL Ser you know knows it SQL
Server it knows what the connection
string is ETC it's not writing the query
now there's we can take advantage of
views in the same way and we can
actually map our objects to views and
have it so we're still executing the
view and it's going to still materialize
the data for us which is really
nice right now there's no better time to
learn a new database with inner systems
Iris you can build the applications you
want however you want them you can
connect your systems use any data model
and apply machine learning so you can
build data intensive and Mission
critical applications in no time level
up your skills with inner systems Iris
the fastest way to build applications
inner systems Iris data
platform Ready Set
code visit intersystems.com Iris to
learn
more yeah so when you were talking about
deciding whether or not to use Entity
framework when you use Entity framework
you could still be using a mix of the
the link query language maybe raw SQL
commands like you said views stored
procedures it's not this this binary
choice where you're saying I'm going to
write everything myself or I'm going to
leave everything dentity framework
absolutely I mean that's yeah the way we
approach programming overall right right
so I've got all of these
wonderful arrows in my quiver to choose
from right and and uh I not I'm not
stuck with one I just leverage you know
using my knowledge and my experience uh
making decision hey this one this tool
right tool for the job right I guess
that's what we you know we've been
saying for decades not just programming
using the right tool for the job but
just because you want to use any
framework doesn't mean you have to use
it all the way through but I think
that's you know that's like again you
know using using C for this and you know
maybe I'll use nodejs or maybe I've got
some really complex mathematical thing
to do for this particular thing I'll use
f or you know some other functional
programming language so we did a a show
back in 2007 about OMS and I know that
you've had a lot of experience both
working with orms and and probably
working with applications without them
just writing SQL directly and so I would
imagine there's been uh a lot of changes
in the last decade or maybe even couple
decades what are some of the big things
that you think have changed with OMS in
in the last 10 or 20 years well I think
something we've been talking about which
is no SQL database has r reduced the
need for
omms right just slice that right off the
top there's so many scenarios where
people don't need relational databases
to solve that and also so this this
interesting right because I I'm not sure
that the answer is about what's happened
with the OMS I think the answer is more
what's evolved with the way we pursue
data and the way we perceive data
machine learning right like the idea of
event sourcing right talk about right
tool for the job like here's my data but
for this this scenario it's going to be
more effective and efficient for me if
that data is stored and relational for
this scenario it'll be more effective if
it's stored as documents right for this
scenario it'd be more effective if it's
text like just a text file oh I forgot
XML just
kidding or Json right what however so I
I I I think that's more what's impacted
OMS than the orms themselves and I know
you know Entity framework is still going
strong and evolving and very very wide
use in the net space some of the ones
that were more popular are are not
really around anymore or not haven't
been updated in a while Dapper gets its
love of course from the stack Overflow
team so I I really think it's more about
the change in how we store data that's
just reduced people's need for OMS but
still like whatever that resource was
you know so 70% of the applications are
still using relational so so there we go
and then and then there's the people
like no matter what like we will never
use an omm we will always use you know
write our own sequel or you know along
with those Legacy databases they have
beautiful stored procedures and Views
and you know finely tuned databases
right and and they'll write the sequel
for you these
people just don't ask me to do it CU I
will never I'll probably never write SQL
that's as good as what Entity framework
with its algorithms and command trees
can figure out on my behalf but there
are plenty of database professionals who
can definitely do that for for somebody
who is working with a relational
database and let's say they worked with
Entity framework or they worked with
hibernate or any number of ORS maybe a
decade ago
is there anything that's changed where
you would say hey this is different
maybe you should give this a second look
yes and again I apologize for not being
able to speak to hibernate like what's
happened to you know how how that is
evolved but when Entity framework first
came out and this was very different
than n hibernate like the net version of
hibernate Entity framework did not have
any concept or or appreciation or
respect
for our objects it was really designed
from the perspective of storing
relational data and it wasn't testable
it just didn't have any patterns well
interestingly I spent a lot of time
researching how Entity framework aligns
with good model design based on how we
design like for domain driven design
Aggregates and some of the things that
we pull in put in place to protect our
entities from bad things people doing
bad things with them and you know so
Entity framework at the beginning did
not give us any way to to do that it
really locked you
into it didn't just lock your data
access in to Entity framework the whole
framework it locked your entire
application in so like your your your
classes all your entities and your
classes had to be completely tied to
Entity Framework order for Entity
framework now that's all decoupled right
so Entity framework uh also we had this
big model this big visual modeler that
in order to create the model you had to
start with an existing database now it's
like look here are my classes I don't
want to design a database I'm designing
software right I'm solving business
problems I have my domain model so you
build your domain model and then say hey
Entity framework here's my domain model
here's my database oh and by the way I
know that by default you're going to
want this to go there and this to go
there but I need to I need to tell you
there's you know a few things I want you
to do a little differently so we have
all of that and we tell Entity framework
has nothing to do with our domain logic
so it's gotten better and better and
more respectful of our code our own you
know our domain logic and our domain
business logic and code and staying out
of the way and that's been a big deal
for me as you know somebody focused on
domain driven design which is um as I'm
building my software I do not want to
think about my data persistence right it
has nothing to do with my domain uh I
like to joke unless I'm building the
next Dropbox competitor right so data
persistence has nothing to do with my
domain so I look to see how well as each
iteration of Entity framework comes out
I look and do some experiments and
research to see how well it its defaults
understand or or map correctly like get
my data in and out of my database
without me having to tweak entity
Frameworks mappings but more importantly
without me having to do anything to my
domain classes in order to satisfy
Entity framework and with each iteration
it's gotten better and better and better
which is nice now one one bit of push
back I had in the early days when I was
talking about Entity framework and
DDD was well you're mapping your domain
directly to the database using Entity
framework you shouldn't do that you
should have a data model and map that
but what's interesting is Entity
framework becomes the data model right
it has all these mapping the mappings of
Entity framework become the data model
so I'm not doing it directly
that is the data model so I it is
solving that problem it's giving me that
separation and there are still some
design some aggregate patterns that
Entity framework for example won't
satisfy in terms of the mappings or
maybe just some problems some business
problems or storage problems that you
have there there are some times when it
just makes sense to you know have
something in between between even if
Entity framework is still in between
that like have a specific data model
because it just handles it differently
so you don't have to change how your
your domain I'm very passionate about
that don't change the domain to make any
framework happy never never never never
could you give a a specific example of
before the objects you would have to
create in order to to satisfy ntity
framework like what what were you
putting into your objects that you
didn't want to put in that I didn't want
to I don't want to well one of the one
of the things that entity Frameworks
mappings could not handle is if you
wanted to
completely isolate or encapsulate a
collection in your entity in your in
your class if you want to encapsu uh if
you want to completely encapsulate The
Collection entity framer couldn't see it
right Entity framework only understood
for example collections but maybe you
want to make it so that you can only
iterate through it enumerate through it
right but if it was an inumerable which
is so that's what you would do like in
your class you would say oh I'm going to
make it an inumerable so nobody can just
add things to it and go around my
business logic which is if you want to
add something you have to go over to
this business logic to make sure all
your invariants are satisfied or
whatever else needs to happen so Entity
framework literally could not see that
and so we struggled with finding ways to
work around that adding stuff or just
giving it up and
saying okay I'm exposing this here
please don't ever use it that way please
please you know you have to tell the
whole team don't ever use it that way
right like ah but with Ed framework core
3 they changed that so I could you could
you can write your class the way way you
want to and you can use the patterns
that we use to encapsulate Collections
and protect them from abuse misuse and
still Entity framework is able to
discover them and understand how to do
all the work it that it needs to do so
that's just an example what you wanted
to do in your domain object is make this
collection be an i innumerable which
makes it so that the user um of that
class is not allowed to add items to it
right the developer right developer
using it add or remove Right add or
remove and uh so you wanted to be able
to control the API for the developer say
that exactly you want to receive this
object and you can you can see what's in
it but you can't add a remove from
it well you can but not directly through
that property right right you'd have to
use a method that has the controls I
refer to it as ADD DD add driven design
right cuz I am a control freak okay I
want to control how anybody's using my
API you wanted to control how people use
the API but if you did that within your
object then n framework would look at
that inumerable and say I I don't know
what this is so I can't map this to the
database it just completely ignores its
existence right so that was one
evolution of Entity framework that mhm
you can do that now and all kinds of all
kinds of other things are there any
other specific examples you can think of
of things that used to be either
difficult to do or might frustrate
people with uh Entity framework that
that are addressed now sure well along
those same lines of encapsulating
properties right so encapsulating
collections was really really hard like
it wasn't hard it was impossible but if
you wanted to either encapsulate
Properties or not even expose properties
you didn't want to expose them all at
all um and you just wanted to have
private Fields you couldn't do anything
like that either but now with this more
modern EF core we could you could
literally have an object a type defined
with
Fields no properties exposing those
fields outside of the API but and but
you can still have you can still persist
data Entity framework is still aware of
them or uh depending on how locked down
like if you made them totally private
you have to tweak the configuration
Entity framework you have tell in your
framework hey this field here I want you
to pay attention to it right so there's
some conventions where it will
automatically recognize it there are
some ways of Designing in your type that
any framework won't see it but there's
you can over override that and tell anti
framework about that so I think that's a
that's a really interesting thing
because there's a lot of scenarios where
people you know want to design their
objects that way and you know again just
so much of that is about
protecting your protecting your API from
misuse or abuse but but not not putting
the onus on the users of your API right
the API will let you do what
you're allowed to do and it won't let
you do what you're not allowed to do you
you had mentioned earlier another big
difference is that it used to be that
you would create your database by
writing SQL and then you would Point
Entity framework to that to generate
your models oh yes the very the very
first iteration that was the only way it
knew how to build a model oh wait there
was a way to build the model a data
model in the design
that's right but then you know
everything's dependent on that model or
on the database instead of no I want to
write my domain logic now Entity
framework not everybody has a brand new
project right but say you get a brand
brand new project and there is no
existing database so you can ask Entity
framework to generate the database based
on you know the combination of its
assumptions from reading your types and
extra configurations you add to Entity
framework and create the database right
so there I hear all the dpas going oh no
no no no no that's not how it works
right but this is this is the simple the
simple path like so first you can have
it create the database and then as you
make changes to your domain Entity
framework has this whole migrations API
that can figure out what has changed
about your domain and then figure out
what SQL needs to be applied to the
database in order to make those
changes so that's that's one path a
Twist on that path of course is you can
create that stuff instead of having
those migrations create the database or
update the database you can just have it
create SQL and hand it to the
professionals and say this is kind of
sort of what I
need right you can do this and then just
make it the way you want it to be just
as long as the mappings still work out
but the other way is you know if you do
have a green field application and you
do have a database already you can
reverse engineer just like we did at the
very beginning but it's a little
different but you can reverse engineer
into a data model which is your
classes and a de a context The Entity
framework configuration so the classes
are you know I refer to those as a stake
in the
ground right because then you could just
take those classes and make them what
you want them to be and then just make
sure that you're still configuring the
mapping so everything lines up so there
are two ways to go still but at the
beginning it was just really I mean
there was this I forgot even that the
designer had the entity data model
designer had a way to design a model
visually and then create both the
database and the classes from it but
that that went away really quickly so it
was essentially you know point to the
database the whole huge database and
create one whole huge data model from it
and that's what everything how
everything would work now a we don't do
that and also we still don't have one
big huge data model right we separation
of concerns again so we have a data
model for this area of work and a data
model for that area of work and you know
they might even point back to their own
own databases right and we start talking
about microservices and Etc yeah so if I
understand correctly it used to be where
you would either use this gooey tool to
build out your your entities or your
database or you would Point Entity
framework at an existing database that
already had tables and columns all
configured right and all of that UI
stuff is gone MH there's I mean some
third- party providers make some UI
stuff but as far as Entity framework is
cons you know Microsoft is concerned
we've got our classes and we've got our
database there's no UI in between it
sounds like the issue with that approach
was that it would generate your domain
models generate your classes but it
would do it in a way that probably had a
whole bunch of Entity framework specific
information in those classes in your
classes yeah okay so much dependencies
in your classes now none of that that
actually they started moving away from
that in the second version of Entity
framework which was called ef4 not two
but it's because it was aligning with
net 4 you know but now
we've now we've got EF core which came
with along with net core which is you
know crossplatform and lightweight and
open source so it sounds like we're
moving in the direction from having
these domain models these classes have
all this Entity framework specific stuff
into it to creating just basic or normal
code uh normal code yeah uh like the
kind of code you would write if you
weren't thinking about Entity framework
or weren't thinking about persistent
specific issues exactly and now with
current orms like Entity framework core
those are able to map to your database
without I guess the term could be
polluting all your classes says yes and
to be fair Entity framework was that was
the evil doer at the beginning of Entity
framework right and hi hibernate didn't
do that and hibernate didn't do that
they totally respected your domain
classes and it was completely separate
so that was the big there was a big I'll
just say a big stink made by the people
who had been using these kinds of
practices already and were using tools
like enh hibernate and and a framework
came around and said oh here's the new
RM on the block from Microsoft everybody
needs to use it and they looked at and
they're like but but but you know
because Entity framework was inserting
itself into its logic into the domain
classes right and the anti framework
team got a lot of big lessons from the
community that was really a aware of
that and I wasn't right I was it was all
new I had never used an OM before so I
was like L dah this is cool this is nice
and you know all these other people were
like going this is terrible why is
Microsoft doing this like I don't
understand right So eventually it
evolved and I learned so much I learned
so much because of them I mean these are
really smart people I have a lot of
respect for so I was like okay they
obviously know what they're talking
about so I got to I got to figure that
out right that's how I ended up on the
path of learning about DDD thank to them
yeah so it sounds like there's been
three versions of Entity framework
there's the initial version that tried
to mix in all these things into your
domain models then there was the second
version which he said was called Entity
framework 4 that that fixed a lot of
those issues and then now we have Entity
framework core I I wonder if you could
explain a little bit about why a third
version was created and what are the the
key differences with with core yeah so
this is this was when Microsoft also at
the same time had taken NET
Framework and Rewritten it to be
crossplatform and open source and use
modern software
practices and at the same time the same
thing happened was done with Entity
framework they they kept many of the
same Concepts but they rewrote it you
know because the codebase was like 10
years old right and also just in Old
thinking so they rewrote it from scratch
keeping a lot of the same concept so
people who were familiar you know who've
been using anti framework they wouldn't
be totally thrown for a loop and you
know so rewrote it with modern software
practices much more open API in terms of
flexibility and open source and because
it was also part of net core
crossplatform
so that was huge and then they've been
building on top of that so Entity
framework the original Entity framework
so I I think it's interesting how you
say there were three so the first
iteration of Entity framework and then
this next one where they really honored
separation of concerns so that was ef4
through
ef6 then they kind of went to a new box
with ef core and start with ef core one
and then two and three and no four and
now it's five so skipping a number again
so ef6 is still around because there's
millions of applications that are using
it and they're not totally ignoring it
as a matter effect they brought ef6 on
top of net core so ef6 is now
crossplatform but it's still in so many
applications and they they've been doing
a little tweaks to it but EF core is
where all the all the work is going now
and it sounds like core is not so much a
dramatically different API for
developers but is rather an opportunity
for them to clean up a lot of technical
debt and absolutely provide that
crossplatform capability at least
initially yeah and enable it to go
forward and to do more be able to
achieve more functionality that people
have wanted but was just literally
wasn't possible with the earlier stack
do you have any examples of a big thing
that people had wanted for a while they
were finally able to do yes and this is
really really specific now because you
know this is about Entity framework um
with the newest version EF Core 5 that's
coming out one thing that people have
been asking for since the beginning of
EF time was when you're eager loading
data so there's a a way of saying you
know bringing related data back in one
query there's actually two ways but
there's one way called a method called
include so including is so that you can
bring back graphs of data instead of
bringing you know go get the customers
now go get their orders and now we need
to merge them together in memory in our
objects so the include method says
please get me the customers and their
orders and include transforms that into
1:34.960> time it taken
microsoft also at the same time it taken
dot net framework and rewritten it
to be cross-platform and open source and
use modern
software practices and at the same time
the same thing happened
was done with entity framework they they
kept many of the same concepts but they
rewrote it
you know because the code base was like
10 years old
right and also just in old thinking
so they rewrote it from scratch keeping
a lot of the same concepts so
people who were familiar you know who've
been using any framework they wouldn't
be
totally thrown for a loop and you know
so we wrote it with modern software
practices much more
open api in terms of flexibility
and open source and because it was also
part of.net core cross-platform
so that was huge and then they've been
building on top of that so
entity framework the original entity
framework so
i i think it's interesting how you say
there were three so
the first iteration of entity framework
and then this next one where they
really honored separation of concerns so
that was the ef4 through ef6
then they kind of went to a new box
with ef core and started with the ef
core
one and then two and three and no four
and now it's five so skipping a number
again
so ef6 is still around because there's
millions of applications that are using
it
and they're not totally ignoring it as a
matter of fact they brought ef6
on top of net core so ef6 is now
cross-platform
but it's still in so many applications
and they
they've been doing a little tweaks to it
but ef core is where
all the all the work is going now and it
sounds like
core is not so much a dramatically
different api for developers but is
rather an
opportunity for them to clean up a lot
of technical debt
and absolutely provide that
cross-platform capability at least
initially
yeah and enable it to go
forward and to do more be able to
achieve
the SQL it's writing so I wonder from
your perspective how much should
developers know about the queries that
are being generated and about equal in
general when you're working with ANM
well I I think it's important you know
if you don't have access to a
professional data professional um it's
important to at least understand how to
profile and how to you know recognize
where performance could be better and
then go seek a professional
right but yeah profiling is really
important so if you've got a team where
you do have a DB
somebody somebody who's really good with
SQL and understands they should be doing
the pro they can be doing the profiling
right capturing it and there's you know
whether if they're using SQL Server they
might just want to use SQL Server
profile or there's all kinds of
thirdparty tools uh there's some
capability built into entity into visual
studio if you're using that or there
there's all kinds of ways to profile
whether you're profiling uh the
performance across the application or
you want to you know hone in on just the
the database activity right because
sometimes the if say there's a
performance problem is it happening in
the database is it happening in memory
is entity Frameworks trying to figure
out the SQL is it happening in memory
after the data has you know the database
did it really fast the data is back in
memory now Entity framework is chugging
along for some reason having a hard time
materializing all those objects and
you know if you said customer include
their orders
there was no way to avoid getting every
single one of their orders for the last
267 years
you're able to do and include so you're
able to join a customer
to their orders but in addition to that
also have some kind of filter like a
where clause
on that that child data let's say quote
you know i'm doing air quotes that child
data that related data so we could never
do that before
so we had to come up with other you know
other ways
to do that so it was it was possible
before but
the way you did it was maybe complicated
or convoluted
and it and it writes good sequel for it
too
yeah you know better than me maybe not
better than
you know many of my really good dba
friends but definitely better than
probably uh better than the majority of
developers who know a little bit of sql
but
uh are definitely not dpas yeah i mean
that's
one of the beauties of a good orm
i guess it doesn't quite get you to
being a dba but it
levels the playing field somewhat well
if i i i can hear my dba friends
cringing at that statement so i will not
agree with that
it doesn't level the playing field but
what it does
is it enables
many developers to write
pretty decent sql how's that
how's that my dba friends yeah i mean i
guess that's a
interesting question in and of itself is
that we're
using these tools like orms that are
generating all this code for us and
we as a developer may not understand the
intricacies of what it's doing
and and the sequel it's writing so i
mean by that and whether you think
that's a that's an issue well that is
exactly what orbs are trying to solve
aiming to solve the mismatch is the
mismatch between the rows and columns in
your database schema and your the shape
of your objects so that's what the
mismatch is and it's an impedance for
getting your data in and out of your
application so the omms are helping you
solve that problem instead of you having
to solve it yourself by you know reading
through your objects and transforming
that into sequel etc etc all those
things we talked about earlier I haven't
heard that term in such a long time
that's so funny to me like I it's funny
that you know we talked about it a lot
when and like in the EF world that was
like what's the F4 it's to take care of
the impedance mismatch duh no we never
said duh I'm just kidding um yeah so but
we we talked about that a lot at the
beginning of Entity Framework history
and yeah I haven't had anybody bring
that up in a long time so I'm actually
grateful you did so maybe we've gotten
to the point where the tools have gotten
good enough where people aren't thinking
so much about that problem because
ideally Entity framework has solved it
enti framework and
hibernate Dapper I think that's a a good
place to to wrap things up so if people
want to learn more about uh what you're
working on or about enity framework or
check out your courses where where
should they head well I spend a lot of
time on Twitter and on Twitter I'm Julie
lurman and I have a website and a Blog
although I have to say I I tweet a lot
more than I blog these days but my
website is thedata
farm.com and I I have a Blog there and
of course uh look me up on plural site
cool well Julie thank you so much 00:59:14.480 align:start position:0%
and you have uh somebody who is more of
an expert like a dba
who can take a look at how are these
things performing
and then if there are issues they can
dive down
into those queries tell the developer
hey i think
you should use a stored procedure here
or a view that that sort of thing yeah
or
you know even kind of expand on that
like just
if you know unless you're solo right or
a tiny little shop
these are how you build teams you've got
qa people you've got testers
you've got data experts you've got
people who
are good at solving certain problems and
everybody
works together as a team for sure yeah
i'm such a libra
why can't we all get along yeah and it
sounds like i mean
it takes care of a lot of the maybe
repetitive or tedious parts of the job
but it does not
remove the need for like you said all
these different
parts of your team whether that's the
dba who can look at the queries
or maybe someone who is more experienced
with profiling so they could see if
object allocation from the orm is a
problem
or all sorts of different more specific
issues that they could dive into a lot
of these
things that that an orm does you were
saying it's about
mapping between typically relational
databases to
objects and applications and something
you hear people talk about sometimes is
something called the
object relational impedance mismatch
and i wonder if you could explain a
little bit about
what people mean by that and whether you
think that's a
that's an issue well that is exactly
what orbs are trying to solve aiming to
solve
the mismatch is the mismatch between the
rows and columns in your database schema
and your the shape of your objects
so that's what the mismatch is and it's
an impedance for
getting your data in and out of your
application so the orms are
helping you solve that problem instead
of you having to solve it yourself
by you know reading through your objects
and transforming that into sql
etc etc all those things we talked about
earlier
i haven't heard that term in such a long
time that's so
funny to me like i it's funny that you
know we talked about it a lot when and
like in the ef world that was like
what's cf4
it's to take care of the impedance
mismatch
duh no we never said done just kidding
um
yeah so but we we talked about that a
lot at the beginning of
entity frameworks history and yeah i
haven't had anybody bring that up in a
long time so
i'm actually grateful you did so maybe
we've gotten to
the point where the tools have gotten
good enough where
people aren't thinking so much about
that problem because
ideally entity framework has solved it
any framework and
hibernate dapper i think that's a
a good place to to wrap things up so
if people want to learn more about
uh what you're working on or about
entity framework or check out your
courses
where should they head well i spend a
lot of time on twitter
and on twitter i'm julie lerman
and i have a website and a blog although
i have to say i
i tweet a lot more than i blog these
days but my website is
thedatafarm.com and i i have a blog
there
and of course uh look me up on
pluralsight
cool well julie thank you so much for
chatting with me it was
great jeremy and you asked so many
interesting questions and also helped me
take some
nice trips into my entity framework past
to remember some
things that i had actually forgotten
about so that was interesting thanks
hopefully
hopefully good memories yeah all good
all good
all right thanks a lot julie thank you
this has been jeremy jung for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
inner systems iris is the fastest way to
build applications
so take advantage of that extra time on
your hands and use it to learn a new
data platform
deliver complex mission critical
applications on the fastest route
possible
with data from any source embedded
analytics and interactive user
interfaces
with systems iris you can connect your
systems
use any data model and apply machine
learning
now's the time to level up your database
platform and try out inner systems iris
so you can collaborate build and deploy
faster than ever before
don't wait any longer level up your
skills with inner systems iris
ready set code
visit intersystems.com try iris to learn
more
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening